One of the reasons why many students struggle
with multiple choice questions with multiple answers is
that they don't know how to take effective
notes as they listen.
Let's take the first question in the previous
exercise to see how we can navigate the
correct answers in all the options.
You can see that the speaker will mention
the animals in the options, however the order
they are mentioned in the audio will not
be A,B,C,D,E.
It will be mixed up.
The best strategy is to take quick notes
next to each option as you hear it.
Now let's go through my note.
The first animal mentioned is the penguin.
My note says average popularity.
This is option A.
We can cross this out because we need
to hear about the most popular animals.
Next we hear about the giraffe.
The speaker says it was still quite popular.
This is option D and we can also
cross it out because quite popular isn't the
same as most popular.
Then we have option E, the tiger.
The note for this is came in a
close second.
Close second is definitely one of the top
ranks so we should consider this a possible
correct answer.
After that is the monkey, option B.
The note says it was near the top.
Again we will cross this out because near
the top is not at the top.
Finally we hear about the lion, option C.
The speaker says it was more popular than
anything else.
This phrase clearly means it was number one
so we will choose this answer.
Normally you might get confused between two options
like E, tiger with the note a close
second and B, monkey with the note near
the top.
These phrases can sound similar when you are
listening quickly but if you take clear notes
as I've done you can see that a
close second is a top rank while near
the top is not.
This helps you confidently choose the correct answers.
To improve your listening skills the task is
to improve your vocabulary.
Remember to pay attention to the language that
emphasizes choices if you hear these phrases.
A rather than B, choose A.
Instead of A, B.
Choose B.
Moreover in the pre-listening part, underlining keywords
and understanding the difference in meaning between the
options are really important.
This helps you listen in an active way
and be more aware of the distractors.
Therefore please focus on keywords that differentiate between
the options.
In case you accidentally miss an answer to
a question, don't panic because you will always
catch the keywords in the questions and the
options to continue listening.
If you can cross out one option out
of the three in a question then it's
clear that your chances of choosing the correct
answer will increase by half.
For challenging questions which require reasoning skills, you
should take notes.
For section 2 where there is only one
speaker, you should take notes next to the
options.
When taking notes you should combine all the
clues you have to make wise choices.
Finally, remember to use the progress tracking chart
when doing the listening test to record your
scores and common mistakes you make.